In the northwest corner of the United States,
في الزاوية الشمالية الغربية للولايات المتحدة،
right up near the Canadian border,
مباشرة بالقرب من الحدود الكندية،
there's a little town called Libby, Montana,
هنالك بلدة صغيرة تدعى ليبي في ولاية مونتانا،
and it's surrounded by pine trees and lakes
ومحاطة بأشجار صنوبر وبحيرات
and just amazing wildlife
وحياة برية مذهلة
and these enormous trees that scream up into the sky.
و هذه الأشجار الضخمة التي تصرخ نحو السماء.
And in there is a little town called Libby,
و هناك توجد بلدة صغيرة تدعى ليبي،
which I visited, which feels kind of lonely,
والتي قمت بزيارتها، وتبعت إحساساً بالوحدة،
a little isolated.
منعزلة بعض الشيء.
And in Libby, Montana, there's a rather unusual woman
و في ليبي بولاية مونتانا، هنالك توجد امرأة غير اعتيادية
named Gayla Benefield.
تدعى غايلا بنفيلد.
She always felt a little bit of an outsider,
كانت دائمًا تشعر بأنها دخيلة على المجتمع،
although she's been there almost all her life,
بالرغم من أنها قد عاشت هناك معظم حياتها،
a woman of Russian extraction.
امرأة من أصل روسي.
She told me when she went to school,
أخبرتني بأنها عندما ذهبت للمدرسة،
she was the only girl who ever chose
كانت الفتاة الوحيدة أبدًا التي اختارت
to do mechanical drawing.
لتقوم بالرسم الصناعي.
Later in life, she got a job going house to house
في وقت لاحق من الحياة، حصلت على وظيفة للذهاب من منزل إلى آخر
reading utility meters -- gas meters, electricity meters.
لتقرأ عدادات المؤسسات العامة -- عدادات الغاز، عدادات الكهرباء.
And she was doing the work in the middle of the day,
وكانت تقوم بهذا العمل في وسط اليوم،
and one thing particularly caught her notice, which was,
وكان هنالك شيء واحد بالذات قد لاحظته، و الذي كان،
in the middle of the day she met a lot of men
أنها قابلت الكثير من الرجال في منتصف اليوم
who were at home, middle aged, late middle aged,
الذين كانوا في المنزل، في منتصف العمر، أواخر منتصف العمر،
and a lot of them seemed to be on oxygen tanks.
والكثير منهم كانوا يستخدمون ما يبدو كخزانات الاكسجين.
It struck her as strange.
صدمها هذا كغرابة.
Then, a few years later, her father died at the age of 59,
ثم، بعد قليل من السنين، توفي والدها عن عمر يناهز 59،
five days before he was due to receive his pension.
خمسة أيام قبل ميعاد استلامه لراتبه التقاعدي.
He'd been a miner.
كان عامل منجم.
She thought he must just have been worn out by the work.
كانت تظن بأنه منهك بسبب العمل.
But then a few years later, her mother died,
لكن لاحقًا بعد عدد من السنين، توفيت والدتهاـ
and that seemed stranger still,
وكان ذلك أغرب،
because her mother came from a long line of people
لأن والدتها تحدرت من خط طويل من الناس
who just seemed to live forever.
الذين ظهر بأنهم يعيشون للأبد.
In fact, Gayla's uncle is still alive to this day,
في الواقع، خالها لا يزال حيًّا إلى هذا اليوم،
and learning how to waltz.
ويتعلم كيف يرقص الفالس.
It didn't make sense that Gayla's mother
إلا إنه من غير المعقول أن والدة غايلا
should die so young.
يجب أن تتوفى في هذا العمر القصير.
It was an anomaly, and she kept puzzling over anomalies.
كانت حالة شاذة، وبقيت متحيرة بالحالات الشاذة.
And as she did, other ones came to mind.
وبينما كانت في تلك الحالة، طرأ آخرون على بالها.
She remembered, for example,
تذكرت، على سبيل المثال،
when her mother had broken a leg and went into the hospital,
عندما كسرت أمها ساقها و ذهبت للمستشفى،
and she had a lot of x-rays,
وتلقت الكثير من الأشعة السينية،
and two of them were leg x-rays, which made sense,
واثنان منهما كانا للساق، و الذي كان منطقيًّا،
but six of them were chest x-rays, which didn't.
لكن ستة منهم كانوا للصدر، والذي كان غير منطقي.
She puzzled and puzzled over every piece
تحيرت مرة تلو الأخرى حول كل قطعة
of her life and her parents' life,
من حياتها وحياة والديها،
trying to understand what she was seeing.
تحاول فهم ما كانت تراه.
She thought about her town.
فكَّرَت حول بلدتها.
The town had a vermiculite mine in it.
تملك البلدة منجمًا للفيرميكيوليت.
Vermiculite was used for soil conditioners,
الفيرميكيوليت كان يستخدم كمحسِّن للتربة،
to make plants grow faster and better.
لجعل النباتات تنمو أسرع وأفضل.
Vermiculite was used to insulate lofts,
الفيرميكيوليت كان يستخدم لعزل الشقق،
huge amounts of it put under the roof
يوضع كمية كبيرة منه تحت السقف
to keep houses warm during the long Montana winters.
لإبقاء المنازل دافئة خلال فصول الشتاء الطويلة في مونتانا.
Vermiculite was in the playground.
الفيرميكيوليت كان في ملاعب الأطفال.
It was in the football ground.
كان في ملعب كرة القدم.
It was in the skating rink.
كان في حلبات التزلج.
What she didn't learn until she started working this problem
ما لم تتعلمه حتى لحظة بدأها العمل على هذه المشكلة
is vermiculite is a very toxic form of asbestos.
هو أن الفيرميكيوليت نوع سام جدًا من الأسبستوس.
When she figured out the puzzle,
عندما اكتشفت حل اللغز،
she started telling everyone she could
بدأت بإخبار كل شخص تستطيع إخباره
what had happened, what had been done to her parents
عما حدث، ما تم فعله لوالديها،
and to the people that she saw on oxygen tanks
و للناس الذين رأتهم بخزانات الاكسجين
at home in the afternoons.
بمسقط رأسها بعد الظهر.
But she was really amazed.
لكنها كانت منذهلة جدًّا.
She thought, when everybody knows, they'll want to do something,
ظنَّت بأنه عندما يعلم، سوف يريدون أن يقوموا بعمل شيء ما،
In fact, she became so annoying
في الواقع، أصبحت هي مزعجةً جدًّا
as she kept insisting on telling this story
عندما أصرًّت على إخبار هذه القصة
to her neighbors, to her friends, to other people in the community,
لجيرانها، لأصدقائها، للأناس الآخرين في المجتمع،
that eventually a bunch of them got together
إلى أن اجتمع مجموعة منهم
and they made a bumper sticker,
وقاموا بعمل ملصقًا لمصد السيارة،
which they proudly displayed on their cars, which said,
والذي قاموا بعرضهم على سياراتهم بكل فخر، والذي قال
"Yes, I'm from Libby, Montana,
"أجل، أنا من ليبي، مونتانا،
and no, I don't have asbestosis."
لا، لست مصابًا بداء الأسبست."
But Gayla didn't stop. She kept doing research.
لكن غايلا لم تتوقف. استمرت بالبحث.
The advent of the Internet definitely helped her.
مجيء الانترنت ساعدها بكل تأكيد.
She talked to anybody she could.
قامت بالتحدث إلى كل شخص استطاعت التحدث إليه.
She argued and argued, and finally she struck lucky
جادلت وجادلت، و أخيرًا صادفها الحظ
when a researcher came through town
عندما عبر باحث خلال البلدة
studying the history of mines in the area,
ليدرس تاريخ المناجم في المنطقة،
and she told him her story, and at first, of course,
و أخبرته بقصتهاـ و في البداية، بكل تأكيد،
like everyone, he didn't believe her,
ككل شخص آخر، لم يصدقها،
but he went back to Seattle and he did his own research
لكنه عاد إلى سياتل وقام ببحثه الخاص
and he realized that she was right.
وأدرك بأنها كانت محقة.
So now she had an ally.
فالآن لديها حليف.
Nevertheless, people still didn't want to know.
على الرغم من ذلك، لا يزال الناس لا يريدون أن يعرفوا.
They said things like, "Well, if it were really dangerous,
قالوا أشياء مثل، "حسنًا، لو كانت بالفعل خطرة،
someone would have told us."
لأخبرنا أحد ما."
"If that's really why everyone was dying,
"إذا كان هذا بالفعل سبب موت الجميع،
the doctors would have told us."
لأخبرنا الأطباء."
Some of the guys used to very heavy jobs said,
بعض الشباب الذين اعتادوا العمل بالمعدات الثقيلة جدًّا قالوا،
"I don't want to be a victim.
"لا أريد أن أكون ضحية.
I can't possibly be a victim, and anyway,
لا يمكن أن أكون ضحية، و على أي حال،
every industry has its accidents."
كل صناعة لها حوادثها."
But still Gayla went on, and finally she succeeded
لكن بقيت غايلا مستمرة، و نجحت في النهاية
in getting a federal agency to come to town
في إقناع وكالة فدرالية للحضور إلى البلدة
and to screen the inhabitants of the town --
وفحص سكان البلدة --
15,000 people -- and what they discovered
15 ألف شخص -- وما اكتشفوه
was that the town had a mortality rate
أن البلدة لديها وفيات بمعدل
80 times higher than anywhere in the United States.
80 ضعف من أي مكان آخر في الولايات المتحدة.
That was in 2002, and even at that moment,
كان ذلك في عام 2002، وحتى في تلك اللحظة،
no one raised their hand to say, "Gayla,
لم يرفع أحد يده ليقول، "غايلا،
look in the playground where your grandchildren are playing.
انظري إلى ملعب الأطفال حيث يلعب أحفادك.
It's lined with vermiculite."
إنها مرصوفة بالفيرميكوليت."
This wasn't ignorance.
لم يكن ذلك جهل.
It was willful blindness.
كان تعامي مقصود.
Willful blindness is a legal concept which means,
تعامي مقصود هو مفهوم قانوني يعني،
if there's information that you could know and you should know
إذا كان هناك معلومة تستطيع معرفتها و يجب عليك معرفتها
but you somehow manage not to know,
لكنك بطريقة ما تجنبت معرفتها،
the law deems that you're willfully blind.
فالقانون يعتبرك متعامٍ قصدًا.
You have chosen not to know.
أنت اخترت عدم المعرفة.
There's a lot of willful blindness around these days.
هناك الكثير من التعامي المقصود هذه الأيام.
You can see willful blindness in banks,
تستطيع رؤية التعامي المقصود في البنوك،
when thousands of people sold mortgages to people
عندما باع الآلاف من الأشخاص قروض عقارية إلى أشخاص
who couldn't afford them.
ليس لديهم القدرة على السداد.
You could see them in banks
تستطيع رؤيتهم في البنوك
when interest rates were manipulated
عندما تم التلاعب بأسعار الفائدة
and everyone around knew what was going on,
وكان الجميع من حولهم يعلم ما كان يحصل،
but everyone studiously ignored it.
لكن واظب الجميع على تجاهله.
You can see willful blindness in the Catholic Church,
تستطيع رؤية التعامي المقصود في الكنيسة الكاثوليكية،
where decades of child abuse went ignored.
حيث عقود من الإساءات للأطفال تم تجاهلها.
You could see willful blindness
تستطيع رؤية التعامي المقصود
in the run-up to the Iraq War.
في التسابق لحرب العراق.
Willful blindness exists on epic scales like those,
التعامي المقصود يتواجد على مقاييس ضخمة كتلك،
and it also exists on very small scales,
وتتواجد أيضًا على مقاييس صغيرة،
in people's families, in people's homes and communities,
في عوائل الأشخاص، في بيوتهم و مجتمعاتهم،
and particularly in organizations and institutions.
و بالذات في المنظمات و المؤسسات.
Companies that have been studied for willful blindness
الشركات التي تم دراستها لبحوث التعامي المقصود
can be asked questions like,
يمكن سؤالهم أسئلة مثل،
"Are there issues at work
"هل هنالك مشاكل في العمل
that people are afraid to raise?"
والتي يخاف الناس من رفعها؟"
And when academics have done studies like this
وعندما قام الأكاديميون بدراسات كهذه
of corporations in the United States,
لشركات في الولايات المتحدة،
what they find is 85 percent of people say yes.
ما وجدوه هو أن 85 بالمئة من الناس أجابوا بـ(نعم).
Eighty-five percent of people know there's a problem,
85 بالمئة من الناس يعلمون بوجود مشكلة،
but they won't say anything.
لكنهم لن يقولوا أي شيء.
And when I duplicated the research in Europe,
وعندما كررت البحث في اوروبا،
asking all the same questions,
بطرح الأسئلة نفسها،
I found exactly the same number.
وجدت هذا العدد نفسه.
Eighty-five percent. That's a lot of silence.
خمسة و ثمانون بالمئة. هذا الكثير من الصمت.
It's a lot of blindness.
الكثير من العمى.
And what's really interesting is that when I go to companies in Switzerland,
المثير حقًّا هو عندما أذهب إلى شركات في سويسرا،
they tell me, "This is a uniquely Swiss problem."
يقولون لي، "هذه مشكلة فريدة لسويسرا."
And when I go to Germany, they say, "Oh yes, this is the German disease."
وعندما أذهب إلى ألمانيا، يقولون لي، "أه أجل، هذا مرض ألماني."
And when I go to companies in England, they say,
وعندما أذهب إلى شركات في انجلترا، يقولون،
"Oh, yeah, the British are really bad at this."
"أه، أجل، البريطانيون سيئون حقًّا في هذا المجال."
And the truth is, this is a human problem.
والحقيقة هي أن هذه مشكلة بشرية.
We're all, under certain circumstances, willfully blind.
جميعنا، في ظل ظروف معينة، نتعامى عن قصد.
What the research shows is that some people are blind
ما يظهره البحث هو أن الناس أعمياء
out of fear. They're afraid of retaliation.
بسبب الخوف. خائفون من الأنتقام.
And some people are blind because they think, well,
وبعض الناس أعمياء لأنهم يظنون
seeing anything is just futile.
أن رؤية شيء ما ليس ذو جدوى.
Nothing's ever going to change.
لن بتغير شيء أبدًا.
If we make a protest, if we protest against the Iraq War,
إذا قمنا بتظاهر، إذا تظاهرنا ضد حرب العراق،
nothing changes, so why bother?
لن يتغير شيء، إذًا لما الإنزعاج؟
Better not to see this stuff at all.
من الأفضل عدم رؤية أي شيء على الإطلاق.
And the recurrent theme that I encounter all the time
والموضوع المتكرر الذي أواجهه دائمًا
is people say, "Well, you know,
هو عندما يقول الناس، "حسنًا، أنت تعلم،
the people who do see, they're whistleblowers,
الناس الذين يرون فعلًا، هم ما يسمون بـ(كاشفي عن الفساد)،
and we all know what happens to them."
وكلنا نعلم ماذا يحدث لهم."
So there's this profound mythology around whistleblowers
إذًا هنالك هذه الخرافة العويصة حول كاشفي الفساد
which says, first of all, they're all crazy.
والتي تقول، قبل كل شيء، جميعهم مجانين.
But what I've found going around the world
لكن ما وجدته يحدث حول العالم
and talking to whistleblowers is, actually,
والتحدث إلى كاشفوا الفساد، واقعًا،
they're very loyal and quite often very conservative people.
هو أنهم أناس مخلصون و غالبًا محافظون.
They're hugely dedicated to the institutions that they work for,
هم متفانون في العمل للمؤسسة التي يعملون من أجلها،
and the reason that they speak up,
والسبب في رفع صوتهم،
the reason they insist on seeing,
السبب في إصرارهم على الرؤية،
is because they care so much about the institution
هو لأنهم يهتمون فعلًا بالمؤسسة
and want to keep it healthy.
ويريدون إبقاءها صحية.
And the other thing that people often say
والأشياء الأخرى التي يقولها الناس غالبًا
about whistleblowers is, "Well, there's no point,
حول كاشفوا الفساد هو، "حسنًا، ليس هناك جدوى،
because you see what happens to them.
لأنك ترى ما يحدث لهم.
They are crushed.
هم مسحوقين.
Nobody would want to go through something like that."
لا أحد يريد أن يواجه شيئًا كهذا."
And yet, when I talk to whistleblowers,
و مع ذلك، عندما أتحدث إلى كاشفوا الفساد،
the recurrent tone that I hear is pride.
النبرة المتكررة التي أسمعها هي الفخر.
I think of Joe Darby.
أتذكر جو داربي.
We all remember the photographs of Abu Ghraib,
كلنا نتذكر الصور من أبو غريب،
which so shocked the world and showed the kind of war
والتي صدمت العالم و أظهرت نوع الحرب
that was being fought in Iraq.
التي تم خوضها في العراق.
But I wonder who remembers Joe Darby,
لكن اتساءل من يتذكر جو داربي،
the very obedient, good soldier
المطيع جدًّا، الجندي الجيد
who found those photographs and handed them in.
الذي وجد تلك الصور و سلمهم للجهات المختصة.
And he said, "You know, I'm not the kind of guy
و قال، "أتعلم، أنا لست ذلك النوع من الرجال
to rat people out, but some things just cross the line.
لأخبر عن الآخرين، لكن بعض الأشياء تتعدى الحدود.
Ignorance is bliss, they say,
يقال بأن الجهل نعمة،
but you can't put up with things like this."
لكن لا يمكنك تحمُّل أشياء كهذه."
I talked to Steve Bolsin, a British doctor,
تحدثت مع ستيف بولسن، الطبيب البريطاني،
who fought for five years to draw attention
الذي حارب لمدة خمس سنين ليجذب الإنتباه
to a dangerous surgeon who was killing babies.
إلى جراح خطر كان يقتل الأطفال.
And I asked him why he did it, and he said,
و سألته لما فعلها، و قال،
"Well, it was really my daughter who prompted me to do it.
"حسنًا، كانت ابنتي بالفعل هي من دفعني إلى فعلها.
She came up to me one night, and she just said,
جاءت إلي في إحدى الليالي، و قالت،
'Dad, you can't let the kids die.'"
(أبي، لا يمكنك ترك الأطفال تموت.)"
Or I think of Cynthia Thomas,
أو أتذكر سينثيا توماس،
a really loyal army daughter and army wife,
إبنة مخلصة جداً لجندي و زوجة لجندي،
who, as she saw her friends and relations
التي رأت عندما عاد أصدقائها و أقاربها
coming back from the Iraq War, was so shocked
عائدون من حرب العراق، صدمت
by their mental condition
بحالتهم العقلية
and the refusal of the military to recognize and acknowledge
و رفض الجيش بالإعتراف و الإقرار
post-traumatic stress syndrome
بإضطراب ما بعد الصدمة
that she set up a cafe in the middle of a military town
الذي دفعها إلى إقامة مقهى في وسط مدينة عسكرية
to give them legal, psychological and medical assistance.
لتعطيهم مساعدة طبية، نفسية، قانونية.
And she said to me, she said, "You know, Margaret,
وقالت لي، "أتعلمين، مارغريت،
I always used to say I didn't know what I wanted to be
كنت دائمًا أقول لنفسي أنني لا أعلم ما أريد أن أكون
when I grow up.
عندما أبلغ.
But I've found myself in this cause,
لكن وجدت نفسي في هذه القضية،
and I'll never be the same."
و لن أكون نفس الشخص أبدًا."
We all enjoy so many freedoms today,
كلنا نستمتع بحريات كثيرة اليوم،
hard-won freedoms:
حريات تم كسبها بصعوبة:
the freedom to write and publish without fear of censorship,
الحرية للكتابة و النشر من دون الخوف من الرقابة،
a freedom that wasn't here the last time I came to Hungary;
حرية لم تكن موجودة آخر مرة أتيت فيها إلى المجر.
a freedom to vote, which women in particular
حرية التصويت، والتي بذاتها حارب النساء
had to fight so hard for;
لها بصعوبة.
the freedom for people of different ethnicities and cultures
الحرية لأناس من مختلف العرقيات و الثقافات
and sexual orientation to live the way that they want.
و الميول الجنسية للعيش بالطريقة التي يريدون.
But freedom doesn't exist if you don't use it,
لكن الحرية غير موجودة إذا لم تستخدمها،
and what whistleblowers do,
و ما يفعله كاشفوا الفساد،
and what people like Gayla Benefield do
و ما يفعله أناس مثل غايلا بنفيلد
is they use the freedom that they have.
هو إستخدام الحرية التي يملكون.
And what they're very prepared to do is recognize
و ما هم جاهزون لفعله هو إدراك
that yes, this is going to be an argument,
أنه أجل، سوف يكون هذا جدالًا،
and yes I'm going to have a lot of rows
و أجل، سوف يكون هنالك الكثير من النزاعات
with my neighbors and my colleagues and my friends,
مع جيراني و زملائي و أصدقائي،
but I'm going to become very good at this conflict.
لكنني سوف أكون جيدةً جدًّا في هذا الصراع.
I'm going to take on the naysayers,
سوف آخذ الرافضون،
because they'll make my argument better and stronger.
لأنهم سوف يجعلون حجتي أفضل و أقوى.
I can collaborate with my opponents
أستطيع التعاون مع معارضيني
to become better at what I do.
لأصبح أفضل فيما أفعله.
These are people of immense persistence,
هؤلاء أشخاص ذوي مثابرة هائلة،
incredible patience, and an absolute determination
صبر ضخم، و إرادة مطلقة
not to be blind and not to be silent.
لئلا يكونوا أعمياء و لئلا يكونوا صامتون.
When I went to Libby, Montana,
عندما ذهبت إلى ليبي، مونتانا،
I visited the asbestosis clinic
زرت عيادة داء الاسبست
that Gayla Benefield brought into being,
التي أوجدتها غايلا بنفيلد،
a place where at first some of the people
مكان حيث كان الناس في البداية
who wanted help and needed medical attention
الذين أحتاجوا للمساعدة و احتاجوا العناية الطبية
went in the back door
ذهبوا إلى الباب الخلفي
because they didn't want to acknowledge
لأنهم لم يريدوا الإعتراف
that she'd been right.
بأنها كانت على حق.
I sat in a diner, and I watched
جلست في مقهى، و راقبت
as trucks drove up and down the highway,
حيث ذهبت الشاحنات عبر الطريق السريع ذهابًا و إيابًا،
carting away the earth out of gardens
ينقلون الأرض من الحدائق
and replacing it with fresh, uncontaminated soil.
و استبدالها بتربة جديدة غير ملوثة.
I took my 12-year-old daughter with me,
أخذت ابنتي ذات الـ12 عامًا معي،
because I really wanted her to meet Gayla.
لأنني أردتها فعلًا أن تقابل غايلا.
And she said, "Why? What's the big deal?"
و قالت، "لما؟ ما الأهمية؟"
I said, "She's not a movie star,
قلت، "هي ليست نجمة سينمائية،
and she's not a celebrity, and she's not an expert,
و هي ليست مشهورة، و هي ليست خبيرة،
and Gayla's the first person who'd say
و غايلا هي الشخص الأول لتقول
she's not a saint.
بأنها ليست قدِّيسة.
The really important thing about Gayla
الشيء المهم جدًا بشأن غايلا
is she is ordinary.
هو بأنها عادية.
She's like you, and she's like me.
هي مثلك، و هي مثلي.
She had freedom, and she was ready to use it."
كان لديها حرية، و كانت جاهزة لاستخدامها."
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)